<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: কোরআন ১৪০০ বছর আগেই বলেছে লোহা মহাকাশ থেকে এসেছে?	</title>
	<atom:link href="/archives/24206/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/archives/24206</link>
	<description>জ্ঞান যেখানে সীমাবদ্ধ, যুক্তি যেখানে আড়ষ্ট, মুক্তি সেখানে অসম্ভব</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 May 2021 13:08:51 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.7.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: hasibul ashraf		</title>
		<link>/archives/24206#comment-4562</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[hasibul ashraf]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 31 Jan 2021 11:43:19 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=24206#comment-4562</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[‘True Skills – Muhammad Ibrahim’ namer channel ti ekti video post koreche jetate tini nastik der 7 ti proshner jobab dite boleche. ami eta amar response hisabe tar comment section e upload korechi. apnar feedack jante parle bhalo hoto(source article hisabe rationalwiki er argument from design use korechi.)-
my answer to this questions- except the number2,every single is a variation of the watchmaker analogy. first lets answerno.2- the Big-Bang theory does not attempt to describe the initial conditions or first cause of the universe. The theory merely addresses the development of the universe from its extremely dense and hot early stages into its present form. (Compare and contrast how the theory of evolution likewise does not concern itself with the origin of life on Earth; but merely with its development after its origin.) It is instructive to think of the Big Bang not as a localized explosion from which all matter moves away, but rather as a uniform expansion of space itself.[notes 1] An observer at any point in the universe sees the same thing: a homogeneous distribution of matter everywhere, with the more-and-more distant parts receding faster and faster.[1][2] notes- In other words space is expanding in all directions equally, not just one, so comparing the expansion of space-time to something like an explosion is misleading at best. But &quot;Big Bang&quot; makes for a catchy concept. so , you have no idea what you are talking about. sources- 1. Scientific American Special Edition — The Cosmic Life Cycle, 1994-2007: &quot;The Evolution of the Universe&quot;, P. James E. Peebles, David N. Schramm, Edwin L. Turner and Richard G. Kron. 2.Cosmos, Carl Sagan. 1985. now,lets give focus to watchmaker analogy. this is also referred to as argument from design , which has also been answered many many times- https://youtu.be/u1szN-oewOs https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2015/02/god-watchmakers-and-the-short-half-lfe-of-technology-metaphors/385408/ also , if we follow your logic , god requires a creator, which cannot be moved without special pleading, for which you do not have any proof.( note ,the burden of proof is on you, you need to prove that the special pleading is , in fact applicable. i talk a bit more about it in the end.) argument from design or watchmaker analogy is also a false analogy. to demonstrate the false analogy more amusingly, let´s rearrange the premises. 1) Humans are complex 2) Humans have sex 3) phones are complex Conclusion: Therefore, watches have sex. 


 more problems Argument from design also fails on another level: it assumes that evidence of design is an objective quality obvious to all viewers. In reality, the ability to discern design is largely a function of familiarity and cultural context. Paley&#039;s &quot;watchmaker&quot; analogy presupposes that anyone finding a complex man-made object would immediately conclude that it was designed; however, there have been cases where observers from cultures unfamiliar with such objects have concluded that they were natural, such as flint tools found in Europe during the 17th century. Not to mention the multitude of phenomena we now know are natural, but which in the past were explained through intelligent design or benevolent creation, such as the Giant&#039;s Causeway , the rock upon which the Kyaiktiyo Pagoda has been built, or the numerous legends explaining how various glacial erratics ended up in their current positions. To illustrate: when you walk through the woods and see a watch, you recognize it as designed not because of its complexity or by contrasting it with the surrounding nature, but because you have seen other watches and all of those watches have, to your knowledge, been engineered by people. It is also clearly not safe to judge whether or not an object is designed purely by its complexity. A perfectly smooth perfect sphere is an extremely simple shape. However, if you found a perfectly smooth perfectly spherical wooden ball in the woods, you would recognize it as most likely not having arisen naturally, but rather having been carved and sanded into that shape. 

The watchmaker analogy, when used in combination with comparison to nature, also fails in that it is self-refuting. If you recognize that a watch is designed because it is more complex than nature, but then you recognize that nature must be designed because it is actually much more complex than a watch, you then have a contradiction (is the watch more complex than nature or nature more complex than a watch?). In the case where you don&#039;t recognize a watch is complex by comparing it to nature but rather you know that watches are designed, you have an argument that is really nothing more than a set of unjustified assertions (A is complex, A is designed, B is more complex than A, therefore B is designed). How exactly do we define &quot;complexity&quot;? Is &quot;complexity&quot; really a good indicator of something being designed? Is it possible for a simple system to naturally become more &quot;complex&quot; over time? Humans also tend to assume deliberate agency is involved in many situations where it is not - this evidences a survival technique: the extra cost of assuming many non-sentient things in the world might actually be sentient and plotting to harm you can outweigh the cost of death should you incorrectly not make that assumption even once. This manifests today when people are afraid of &quot;bumps in the night&quot;, or, more humorously, when people yell at their computers for failure to function as they wish. The analogy also fails due to being extremely reductive; a watch does not just imply a watchmaker, instead being the culmination of many generations of craftspeople and inventors working in a great many fields (gears, smelting, springs, time-keeping, mathematics, measurement, machine tools...), the watch simply being the final link (to date) in a chain or a web of uninterrupted, progressively different devices - each adapted to specific demands (sound familiar?). Indeed, if the same logic is used but the device found is scaled up to the point no single human could hope to build such a device in one lifetime (say, an aircraft carrier) one would have to conclude within the analogy that the machine was the result of divine creation, since clearly no single mortal creator could have made it. This would presumably make it the work of double God. Most design arguments mangle real technology in a similar way: for example, a modern steel mill could be demonstrated to be the work of a divine being because parts of the mill are made from steel, but making steel requires a steel mill. The creationist argument would be that the mill must have been created by a God who could pull steel from the netherverse, and this would obviously be a much better explanation than there being some earlier and more primitive method of steel-making that did not require steel parts, because they said so. Put all that back into a Paley-style counter-analogy: a watch results from one or more generations of artificers chanting the magic formula: &quot;Let there be a sundial.&quot; Even assuming that the quality of design is objective and obvious to all viewers, a third weakness in the argument from design is the premise that the life-forms that exist have some degree of &quot;perfection&quot; only attainable if they were designed. 

There is a fable from Aesop illustrating the dubiousness of this notion. The fable was set at a time when the Greek pantheon were busy about the work of creation. Zeus had made the first man, Poseidon the first bull, and Athena the first house. They could not agree as to which of these creations were the best, so they called in Momus , the literal god of snark, as a judge. Momus made the following judgments: Zeus&#039;s man was not good, because his heart had not been placed outside his body to allow others to read his evil intents. Poseidon&#039;s bull was not good, because its horns had not been set below its eyes so it could see where to strike. Athena&#039;s house was not good, because it was not a mobile home and could not be moved away from disagreeable neighbors. Creationists would probably be inclined to do what Zeus did just then: remove Momus&#039;s right to judge and kick him out. 


Occam&#039;s Razor In The Blind Watchmaker, Richard Dawkins writes: “”But of course any God capable of intelligently designing something as complex as DNA/protein replicating machine must have been at least as complex and organized as the machine itself. Far more so if we suppose him additionally capable of such advanced functions as listening to prayers and forgiving sins. To explain the origin of the DNA/protein machine by invoking a supernatural Designer is to explain precisely nothing, for it leaves unexplained the origin of the Designer. You have to say something like &quot;God was always there&quot;, and if you allow yourself that kind of lazy way out, you might as well just say &quot;DNA was always there&quot;, or &quot;Life was always there&quot;, and be done with it. To say that that the undoubtedly complex Designer doesn&#039;t need to be designed is to invalidate the very premise of the argument (it makes use of the fallacy of Special pleading, in other words): that complex things must have designer(s). If one can imagine something complex that doesn&#039;t have to have been designed, as proponents of this argument would believe, then who&#039;s to say that anything complex needs to have a designer?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>‘True Skills – Muhammad Ibrahim’ namer channel ti ekti video post koreche jetate tini nastik der 7 ti proshner jobab dite boleche. ami eta amar response hisabe tar comment section e upload korechi. apnar feedack jante parle bhalo hoto(source article hisabe rationalwiki er argument from design use korechi.)-<br />
my answer to this questions- except the number2,every single is a variation of the watchmaker analogy. first lets answerno.2- the Big-Bang theory does not attempt to describe the initial conditions or first cause of the universe. The theory merely addresses the development of the universe from its extremely dense and hot early stages into its present form. (Compare and contrast how the theory of evolution likewise does not concern itself with the origin of life on Earth; but merely with its development after its origin.) It is instructive to think of the Big Bang not as a localized explosion from which all matter moves away, but rather as a uniform expansion of space itself.[notes 1] An observer at any point in the universe sees the same thing: a homogeneous distribution of matter everywhere, with the more-and-more distant parts receding faster and faster.[1][2] notes- In other words space is expanding in all directions equally, not just one, so comparing the expansion of space-time to something like an explosion is misleading at best. But &#8220;Big Bang&#8221; makes for a catchy concept. so , you have no idea what you are talking about. sources- 1. Scientific American Special Edition — The Cosmic Life Cycle, 1994-2007: &#8220;The Evolution of the Universe&#8221;, P. James E. Peebles, David N. Schramm, Edwin L. Turner and Richard G. Kron. 2.Cosmos, Carl Sagan. 1985. now,lets give focus to watchmaker analogy. this is also referred to as argument from design , which has also been answered many many times- <a href="https://youtu.be/u1szN-oewOs" rel="nofollow ugc">https://youtu.be/u1szN-oewOs</a> <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2015/02/god-watchmakers-and-the-short-half-lfe-of-technology-metaphors/385408/" rel="nofollow ugc">https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2015/02/god-watchmakers-and-the-short-half-lfe-of-technology-metaphors/385408/</a> also , if we follow your logic , god requires a creator, which cannot be moved without special pleading, for which you do not have any proof.( note ,the burden of proof is on you, you need to prove that the special pleading is , in fact applicable. i talk a bit more about it in the end.) argument from design or watchmaker analogy is also a false analogy. to demonstrate the false analogy more amusingly, let´s rearrange the premises. 1) Humans are complex 2) Humans have sex 3) phones are complex Conclusion: Therefore, watches have sex. </p>
<p> more problems Argument from design also fails on another level: it assumes that evidence of design is an objective quality obvious to all viewers. In reality, the ability to discern design is largely a function of familiarity and cultural context. Paley&#8217;s &#8220;watchmaker&#8221; analogy presupposes that anyone finding a complex man-made object would immediately conclude that it was designed; however, there have been cases where observers from cultures unfamiliar with such objects have concluded that they were natural, such as flint tools found in Europe during the 17th century. Not to mention the multitude of phenomena we now know are natural, but which in the past were explained through intelligent design or benevolent creation, such as the Giant&#8217;s Causeway , the rock upon which the Kyaiktiyo Pagoda has been built, or the numerous legends explaining how various glacial erratics ended up in their current positions. To illustrate: when you walk through the woods and see a watch, you recognize it as designed not because of its complexity or by contrasting it with the surrounding nature, but because you have seen other watches and all of those watches have, to your knowledge, been engineered by people. It is also clearly not safe to judge whether or not an object is designed purely by its complexity. A perfectly smooth perfect sphere is an extremely simple shape. However, if you found a perfectly smooth perfectly spherical wooden ball in the woods, you would recognize it as most likely not having arisen naturally, but rather having been carved and sanded into that shape. </p>
<p>The watchmaker analogy, when used in combination with comparison to nature, also fails in that it is self-refuting. If you recognize that a watch is designed because it is more complex than nature, but then you recognize that nature must be designed because it is actually much more complex than a watch, you then have a contradiction (is the watch more complex than nature or nature more complex than a watch?). In the case where you don&#8217;t recognize a watch is complex by comparing it to nature but rather you know that watches are designed, you have an argument that is really nothing more than a set of unjustified assertions (A is complex, A is designed, B is more complex than A, therefore B is designed). How exactly do we define &#8220;complexity&#8221;? Is &#8220;complexity&#8221; really a good indicator of something being designed? Is it possible for a simple system to naturally become more &#8220;complex&#8221; over time? Humans also tend to assume deliberate agency is involved in many situations where it is not &#8211; this evidences a survival technique: the extra cost of assuming many non-sentient things in the world might actually be sentient and plotting to harm you can outweigh the cost of death should you incorrectly not make that assumption even once. This manifests today when people are afraid of &#8220;bumps in the night&#8221;, or, more humorously, when people yell at their computers for failure to function as they wish. The analogy also fails due to being extremely reductive; a watch does not just imply a watchmaker, instead being the culmination of many generations of craftspeople and inventors working in a great many fields (gears, smelting, springs, time-keeping, mathematics, measurement, machine tools&#8230;), the watch simply being the final link (to date) in a chain or a web of uninterrupted, progressively different devices &#8211; each adapted to specific demands (sound familiar?). Indeed, if the same logic is used but the device found is scaled up to the point no single human could hope to build such a device in one lifetime (say, an aircraft carrier) one would have to conclude within the analogy that the machine was the result of divine creation, since clearly no single mortal creator could have made it. This would presumably make it the work of double God. Most design arguments mangle real technology in a similar way: for example, a modern steel mill could be demonstrated to be the work of a divine being because parts of the mill are made from steel, but making steel requires a steel mill. The creationist argument would be that the mill must have been created by a God who could pull steel from the netherverse, and this would obviously be a much better explanation than there being some earlier and more primitive method of steel-making that did not require steel parts, because they said so. Put all that back into a Paley-style counter-analogy: a watch results from one or more generations of artificers chanting the magic formula: &#8220;Let there be a sundial.&#8221; Even assuming that the quality of design is objective and obvious to all viewers, a third weakness in the argument from design is the premise that the life-forms that exist have some degree of &#8220;perfection&#8221; only attainable if they were designed. </p>
<p>There is a fable from Aesop illustrating the dubiousness of this notion. The fable was set at a time when the Greek pantheon were busy about the work of creation. Zeus had made the first man, Poseidon the first bull, and Athena the first house. They could not agree as to which of these creations were the best, so they called in Momus , the literal god of snark, as a judge. Momus made the following judgments: Zeus&#8217;s man was not good, because his heart had not been placed outside his body to allow others to read his evil intents. Poseidon&#8217;s bull was not good, because its horns had not been set below its eyes so it could see where to strike. Athena&#8217;s house was not good, because it was not a mobile home and could not be moved away from disagreeable neighbors. Creationists would probably be inclined to do what Zeus did just then: remove Momus&#8217;s right to judge and kick him out. </p>
<p>Occam&#8217;s Razor In The Blind Watchmaker, Richard Dawkins writes: “”But of course any God capable of intelligently designing something as complex as DNA/protein replicating machine must have been at least as complex and organized as the machine itself. Far more so if we suppose him additionally capable of such advanced functions as listening to prayers and forgiving sins. To explain the origin of the DNA/protein machine by invoking a supernatural Designer is to explain precisely nothing, for it leaves unexplained the origin of the Designer. You have to say something like &#8220;God was always there&#8221;, and if you allow yourself that kind of lazy way out, you might as well just say &#8220;DNA was always there&#8221;, or &#8220;Life was always there&#8221;, and be done with it. To say that that the undoubtedly complex Designer doesn&#8217;t need to be designed is to invalidate the very premise of the argument (it makes use of the fallacy of Special pleading, in other words): that complex things must have designer(s). If one can imagine something complex that doesn&#8217;t have to have been designed, as proponents of this argument would believe, then who&#8217;s to say that anything complex needs to have a designer?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
